Contact

9971966473 (Mobile) catchkv@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/shyamkv-8656813a (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Leadership

English

Key Account Management

Languages

English (Full Professional)

Marathi

Spanish

Certifications

Learning ITIL®

Learning Git and GitHub

Shyam KV

Additional Director, Technical Training. Shimla

Summary

Passionate and diversified Military Officer with 17 years of proven effective leadership in :

Technology management | Project management | Data analytics | Product development & Penetration | Procurement & vendor management | Stake holder management | Supply chain management | Logistics management | Human Resource management | MIS | Program management | Solutions Architect | Training & Mentoring | Innovative Lead.

Developed various Operational solutions for Data management, Incident management & Security control.

Experience

Indian Army.

17 years 2 months

Additional Director, Technical Training July 2020 - Present (1 month)

Shimla, Himachal Pradesh, India

Formulate concepts and training doctrines of major training academies.

Enable paradigm shift by keeping in pace with latest technological updates.

Empower end users and keeping them abreast with future advancements and enabling them to take large strides by upskilling with competetive spirit.

Senior Technical Consultant June 2019 - June 2020 (1 year 1 month) India

Defined the standards for application architecture, database design, development and infrastructure deployment of IT Projects. Arrived at the optimal and robust IT Infrastructure based on the existing scenario. Supported the roll out of nationwide IT projects. Analyzed existing/ proposed projects with regards to strategic control, security, disaster recovery and business continuity. Ensured that individual project level initiatives are interoperable,

standardized, scalable and secure across various areas of software, hardware and infrastructure

Senior Operations Manager January 2019 - June 2020 (1 year 6 months)

Madhya Pradesh, India

App development management for recording and monitoring of user information on critical data for HR management and designed modules for update and store using Firebase database.

Involved in in-house design of Automated Computer Surveillance vision for carrying out perimeter surveillance of establishment with a perimeter of 10 kms in operational area using Python & XML programming.

Upgraded the Learning management module to assist in carrying out training of large group of users in upskilling using Microsoft Visual sudio.

Designed and implemented Logistics chain using WIX.com for empowering users to feed essential services online thereby saving huge amount of resources for coordinating the same.

Research and Development Project Manager June 2018 - December 2018 (7 months) Manipur, India

Evaluated and vetted various products for usage as convertiplanes to navigate, monitor and feed recorded data captured by day/night camera for usage of surveillance purpose.

Tested various parameters with respect to individual uplink & downlink frequency for obtaining and storing desired data in designated data storage. Formulated a technical manual for Vetting, procedural testing & assessing of products considering the technical criticality & constraints of operational terrain.

Enterprise & Solutions architect July 2017 - July 2018 (1 year 1 month)

IT equipment procurement, handling and exploitation.

Implementing & Practicing Six sigma applications in Military Recovery operations.

Designing and conducting Training standards of using technical infrastructure for military training in real time scenario.

Joint Director January 2018 - June 2018 (6 months) Member of core group involved in formulation of strategic level policy decisions on operational planning and utilization of technical resources and manpower. Optimized efficiency through service design. Evaluated and executed office workflow mgt system. Quality Assurance, testing, coordination with QA experts. Provided recommendations. Planned, allocated and monitored budget under multiple heads (short/long term).

Technical Project Program Manager January 2017 - June 2017 (6 months)

Nagaland, India

Involved in design and setup of Mail servers for all departments of establishment using Zimbra mail server and further upgraded File Management setup in the same for smooth flow of technical updates. Enhanced operational efficiency by establishing Thin client setup using openthinclient.

Designed and setup automated application for logging vehicle exploitation details with the help of RFID tags for the purpose of monitoring on controlled usage & prompting for timely service mapping basing on pre-fed parameters as per the technical manual.

Data Analyst & Manager, Business Intelligence January 2015 - December 2016 (2 years) New Delhi, Delhi, India

Data Analysis, Collation, Data statistics, Business Intelligence, Reliability Engineering, Performance Indiactor study, Effect of KPIs on Equipment performance etc.,

Created Data analytics & visualization requirements including drill down.

Ensured resolution of hardware and system downtime related problems with minimal lag times.

Process reviews and application configuration discussions with clients.

Business Analysis: Data & Statistical Analysis (Descriptive, Diagnostic, Predictive and Prescriptive); SEM.

Provided industry analysis & strategic guidance to builders, providers and users of data center technologies. Maj AOR incl emerging architectures and technologies, digital strategy, cost containment & contract negotiation. Covered cloud computing, virtualization, sustainability & Infrastructure consolidation.

Technologies/Products evaluated : Hadoop, Spark, Splunk, Alteryx, Tableau

Jt Director, Project management January 2014 - December 2016 (3 years) New Delhi, Delhi, India

Selected as the Project Manager for the first implemention of ERP (SAP)/BI(BOBJ) solution at a 500+ strong organisation.

Responsible for contract mgt, business process blueprinting, execution including hardware/software/licence mgt, data migration strategy, testing, training and vendor mgt (Implementation, Deployment & Operational Mgt). Resolved issues between stakeholders and managed multi-vendor environment. The ERP/ BI & Analytics systems churn out integrated real-time information resulting in organizational productivity.

Prepared project reports & documents including manuals, customer query data, logs/issues and their resolution.

Head Of Product Development

March 2014 - December 2015 (1 year 10 months)

New Delhi, Delhi, India

Evolved process of refining and upgradation till final rolling over of Integrated Web Application across Pan-Army.

Responsible for effective functioning of various MRO modules along with HR modules and streamlining common platform to port relevant data inputs for deriving data analytics required for decision making.

Test for app compatibility with various versions of Windows.

Implemented e-Office application using PostgreSQL at Country Head
Office and saved a tune of 50 Lakh rupees against licence procurement for
upgradation of existing software application

Carried large no of training sessions for users and mentored various department heads on exploitation of services.

Head Reliability & Maintenance department April 2012 - December 2013 (1 year 9 months)

Jammu, Jammu and Kashmir (state), India

Responsible for all functions of a Business Unit including Leadership, Strategic Planning, Risk assessment, Finance & Budgeting, Project mgt, Process mgt, Sourcing & procurement, Brand management and HRD. Improved shop floor output through Kanban.

Practiced Six Sigma, CMMi & P-CMM to deliver through improved processes. Designed and hosted website for data integration of all processes being fed from sub-units for carrying out analytical derivation of sustenance state of equipment using Visual studio, C# & ASP.NET

Designed Integrated Electronic Training Module(IETM) and further upgraded the same regularly for regular reference of various technical teams.

Manager – IT Ptojects
July 2011 - March 2012 (9 months)

Keen observer of technology patterns, consumer trends & requirements. Expertise in designing robust data security setup using Backtrack programming. Designed and established a local website on XAMPP server(Cross Platform, Apache, MySQL, PHP & Perl) for demonstrating various tools for training of team members.

Senior Executive Human Resources July 2010 - June 2011 (1 year) Arunachal Pradesh, India

Established complete setup of Maintenance, Repair and Operations model for upkeep and maintenance of wide range of critical equipment in challenging operational scenario in definite time frame. Designed and fabricated critical testing tools and kits for enhancing the operational efficiency of equipment being exploited for various roles.

Senior Technology Manager July 2008 - June 2010 (2 years) Gujarat, India

Expertise in integrating technologies related to mechanical equipment with IT interface to derive intelligence for operations and also involved in training team members in the same. Designed IT applications automating the operations related to HR management, Logistics management and finance management.

Head, Design & Maintenance July 2006 - June 2008 (2 years) Srinagar, India

Responsible for ensuring uptime and operation of Direction Finding base equipment alongwith imported military equipment from multiple countries of origin. It has lead to real time data feed from remote locations to assist in supplying critical operational information. Coordinated with multiple agencies in using the input to address the logistic challenges for creating a stable flow of communication.

Head, Operational Services November 2005 - June 2006 (8 months) Sikkim, India

Ensured a robust supply chain management with various agencies for remote sustenance during mobilisation. Inspired and led the team as team leader by setting personal example thereby ensuring timely completion of many complex and challenging (logistic, administrative & technical) projects and assignments.

Team Lead

June 2003 - October 2005 (2 years 5 months)

Jammu and Kashmir (state), India

In-Charge of 100+ team members administering and leading in operations. Enhanced robust security setup by designing network for Installing PIR (Passive Infrared sensors) along with Perimeter Intrusion detection system (PIDS).

Education

Indian Institute of Management, Indore

Management Development Programme, Logistics, Materials, and Supply Chain Management · (2018 - 2018)

Shivaji University

Bachelor's Degree, Bachelor of Electronics Engineering · (1999 - 2003)

VMR College, Warangal

Associate's Degree, Computer Engineering · (1996 - 1999)

LEM High School

High Schooling · (1991 - 1996)

Sharon High School

· (1985 - 1990)